PAULO CUELLAS

E-mail: paulo.cuellas@pamzc.com · Location: Toronto On M2J 1V3 · Phone: (647) 675 0204
LinkedIn · Portfolio · Website · GitHub

Multi-skilled Data Engineer with an excellent track record in Database Management and Systems Analysis. Knowledgeable, enthusiastic, and extremely committed professional implementing high-quality databases and applications for customers transforming data in results, reaching a successful record in IT projects. A proactive leader always inspiring team collaboration toward the common goal. Acquired experience in all system development life cycle (SDLC).

TECHNICAL SKILLS

RDBMS: Oracle, PostgreSQL, MS SQL Server, and MySQL; **Programming**: Python, HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript: Nodejs, D3, Leaflet, GeoJSON, Plotly, React, and jQuery; **Operations Systems**: Windows and Linux; **Cloud Computing**: Amazon AWS; **Familiarity** with MongoDB, Java/Spring MVC, PHP/Laravel 5.0, C#, and C++.

EDUCATION

- Data Analytics and Visualization Certification at University of Toronto (Anticipated Graduation Date: Nov -2019);
- Oracle Database SQL and PL/SQL Developer Associate Certifications 2018;
- AWS Solutions Architect, Developer, and SysOps Administrator Associate Certifications 2017;
- Scrum Master Certification 2014;
- MBA Excellence in Project Management and Organizational Processes 2015;
- Diploma in Data Processing Faculty of Technology of Sao Paulo Brazil.

EXPERIENCE

CONSULTANT - DATABASE DEVELOPER

Youdb Marketing agency – SP Brazil - 04/2017 – 07/2018

- Performed data sources documentation analyses to build ETL processes to import and export data;
- Modelled and created databases to sales analysis, to classify customers, and to get insights for marketing campaigns;
- Implemented triggers, functions, procedures, views, and complex queries for different RDBMS;
- Tested and validated data flow over systems to ensure data quality and data integrity.

IT MANAGER

Youdb Marketing agency – SP Brazil - 03/2014 – 12/2016

- Reduced the monthly cost by one third after moving and realigning the underperforming IT infrastructure to AWS;
- Developed, adapted, and constructed customized ETL software as per organizational requirements;
- Built processes to extract mailing lists for marketing campaigns, conducted data analysis, and generated standard as well as custom reports for the marketing team;
- Successfully led database audit in compliance with customer privacy and security requirements.

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

SCRUM MASTER

Youdb Marketing agency - SP Brazil - 06/2009 - 2/2014

SENIOR SYSTEM ANALYST

Ibiz Technology – SP Brazil - 11/2002 – 3/2009

PROJECTS

EMPLOYEES DB ANALYSIS - GitHub

- **Description**: the purpose of this project was evaluating an employee's CSV data set with 300,024 records to look for any sort of data inconsistency. As a result, an incoherency between the salaries amount and job positions was detected.
- Activities: analyzed the CSV files structure to have information to create the Entity-Relationship Diagrams and the database; Implemented a schema SQL script to recreate the database structure and import all the files in one shot; wrote a query script for analysis and plotted a bar chart to expose the result evidence.
- **Technologies**: PostgreSQL 11, SQLAlchemy, Matplotlib, and Pandas (Python).

RENNER - DATABASE MARKETING

- **Description**: Renner is the largest Brazilian retail chain of clothing and has more than 360 stores. It required to implement a centralized database importing data from more than 35 sources. Since the new database has a wide variety of information, it has been used for many purposes as customer retention, Recency, Frequency and Monetary analysis, provide insights and support for marketing campaigns, perform score and customer segmentation, realize customer preferences, experience and satisfaction, and get ideas for branding strategy.
- Activities: created the database Entity-Relationship Model based on the data sources documentation and business rules; managed to solve technical problems of high impact on the deadline of a milestone to import file with more than 50Gb; as a team leader instructed and transferred all technical knowledge to the team so they will be able to monitor and to support the project; configured and adjusted ETL applications; created materialized views; and developed procedures and queries to import files from data sources and to perform business rules.
- Technologies: Oracle, Toad Database Modeler, SQL Developer, Linux, and Perl.

NESTLÉ - DATABASE MARKETING

- Description: the main goal of this project was to create a centralized database able to provide information
 to get insights for marketing campaigns and product branding strategy, perform customer segmentation,
 manage the quarterly distribution of 300k magazines for customers, and provide information for the CRM
 system.
- Activities: designed the database structure based on the data sources documentation; created the
 infrastructure at AWS to support the database and ETL applications; implemented match keys rules for data
 deduplication and data treatment; wrote procedures and functions to perform data cleansing,
 standardization, deduplication, and to extract customers lists for campaigns; adjusted ETL applications and
 integration systems related to the project.
- Technologies: PostgreSQL, Microsoft SQL Server, Linux, AWS, Perl, PHP, Java, and C#.

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

COMMUNITY MATTERS TORONTO (DEZ 2018 – JAN 2019)

• Performed a role as an English teacher to help Syrian families in adjusting to their new lives in Toronto.